<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The oration of the most noble and reverende father in God the Lorde Cardinalles Grace of Lorrain made and pronounced in thassemblie [sic] at Poyssi, the kyng beyng present, the sixtene daye of Septembre, in the yeare of our Lorde 1561 / translated out of Frenche into Englishe by T.S.</title>
            <author>Guise, Charles de, Cardinal de Lorraine, 1525-1574.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5010.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22177461</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22177461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18448)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1748:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The oration of the most noble and reverende father in God the Lorde Cardinalles Grace of Lorrain made and pronounced in thassemblie [sic] at Poyssi, the kyng beyng present, the sixtene daye of Septembre, in the yeare of our Lorde 1561 / translated out of Frenche into Englishe by T.S.</title>
                  <author>Guise, Charles de, Cardinal de Lorraine, 1525-1574.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Jugge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1561?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poissy, Colloquy of, 1561.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>THE ORA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE MOST NOBLE AND REVERENDE</hi> FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in <hi>GOD</hi> the lorde Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles grace of Lorrain, made and pronounced in thaſſemblie at Poyſſi, the Kyng beyng preſent, the ſixtene days of Septembre, In the yeare of our Lorde <hi>1561.</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated out of Frenche into Engliſhe. by T. S.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:25224:2"/>
            <p>THis preſent daye being the eight of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober. 156<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. The kinge beynge at Saint Germyne in Laye did permit &amp; geue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to William Morel his printer dwelling at Paris to printe or cauſe to be printed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racion made by the cardinals grace of Lotha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe: in the aſſemble at Poiſſy the 16. daye of September laſt paſt, &amp; the ſame to put abroade &amp; vtter, forbidding all other printers the ſame to imprinte or cauſe to bee imprinted, or ſelle without licence or ſufferaunce of the ſaid Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, and his maieſty hath geuen me in comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement hereof to make aſmuch expedicion as I conueniently coulde.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>De Laubeſpine,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:25224:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>YRE,</hi> we acknowleadge you for oure ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne and naturall lorde, and confeſſe oure ſelues to be your moſt humble and obediente ſubiectes and ſeruauntes: And the fidelitie whiche we haue ſworne, and ſolemnely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed vnto your grace, we will neuer gaine go it. After our example then, and accordyng to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of God, whiche we announce, all ye that be preſente,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and all thoſe lykewiſe that bee vnder your maieſties rule &amp; gouernemente in this moſſe chriſten realme, be ye for the loue of God ſubiectes to all policie and humaine order, whether it be to the kynge, as to the head and ſoueraigne: or vnto theim whiche vnder hym ſupplie the chiefe places nerte his perſone, or els vnto other by hym eſtabliſhed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the prouinces, euery one accordynge to his charge, as vnto them whiche be ſent by hym, to the punyſhyng of euyll doers, and to the praiſe of them that do well. For ſuch is the will of God, that in doyng well you ſhall ſtoppe the mouthe to the ignorant and foolyſhe: All this purpoſe the apoſtle ſaint Peter concludeth in theſe fower words,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> Feare God, and honor the Kyng, as though he wold ſaye, Honor the kyng, for that ye ought to ſcare God. It is he,<note place="margin">Pro. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by whom kynges do rule: And they that make lawes, ordeyn iuſt thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wherby princis doo commaunde, and the mightie doo iudge the earth, wherof he that will ſeke thoriginall muſt nedes confeſſe, that all power is geuen of our Lorde God, and the vertue &amp; ſtrength cometh from aboue.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ro<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is he (ſaith Dauid) that geueth ſaufetie to kinges, and inſtructeth my handes to fight, &amp; maketh my ſingers to ſerue in the warre. To be ſhort, fithens that all ſuperior and hygh power is of God, principally then is the power of kynges ordeined by hym: wher vnto if any maketh reſiſtence, dothe withſtande his ordinance, and purchaſeth to himſelfe damnation: Let vs be therfore to your maieſtie faithfull and obediente ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, not onely for not prouoking your anger, but alſo for conſcience ſake. Notwithſtanding remembre ſyre, that you are not onely a miniſter of God, and of oure Lorde Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:25224:3"/>
Chriſte,<note place="margin">The due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a Kyng to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the churche, &amp; of his authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tee there Eſa 49 60</note> but alſo of his Chirch, the whiche you noriſhe and conſerue: you are therof a ſonne, and not a lorde, a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and not a head, as by his prophete long tyme ſithens, he warned the chirche whyche ſhoulds be aſſembled of the Gentils. For Eſaie ſayth, The kynges ſhalbe thy nourſes, and ſhal ſubmitte them ſelues to do thee honor and ſeruice. The kynges ſhall be broughte vnto thee, and ſhall obeye thee. And the people and realme that ſhall not ſerue thee, ſhall peryſhe, and there ſhall be made ſuche waſte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that no habitation there ſhall bee founde. Which ſaying our firſt and moſte holy ancient Byſhoppes aduentured to proteſte before their myghtieſt and moſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Emperors,<note place="margin">23 q. 8. cap conuen<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and thoſe Emperoures accepted the ſame in good parte. Sainct Ambroſe ſpeakyng of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Valentinian the yonger, and of Iuſtinian his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith thus: What name or title more honorable maye an Emperor attribute to hym ſelfe, then to bee called the Sonne of the Churche, whiche was ſpoken withoute of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and the ſame ryghte thankefully accepted. For the Emperor is within the Churche, and not aboue. The ſame Saint Ambroſe in a requeſt preſented to the ſame Emperor refuſed his iudgement in his diſputation with Aurentius an Arrian byſhoppe:<note place="margin">Epi 32</note> Foraſmuche (ſayth he) as in cauſes of Faithe and of the Churche, Byſhoppes do iudge of the laitie, and not the laitie in their conſiſtories, &amp; aſſemblies do iudge of Byſhops. And this, ſaith he, none will cal in doubte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wel ordered courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil folow the good auncient cuſtomes and obſeruations. Way enge well then theſe thynges, what is he, that in cauſe of faithe will denye, that Byſhoppes haue not accuſtomed to iudge of Chriſtian Emperors, and not the Emperours of Byſhoppes? In this Conſiſtorie <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> hathe not accuſtomed to occupye the place of a partie, but rather of a Iudge. If ye treate with hym I haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that it oughte to bee in the Churche, whyche my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers haue doone. If it bee to haue conference in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faithe, that conference oughte to bee made with
<pb facs="tcp:25224:3"/>
the prieſtes.<note place="margin">VVhat in g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments in maters of faithe the olde chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and in vvhat eſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation they had their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops &amp; prieſtes. Ruf. li. 10 ca. 2. Tripar. li. 2, ca, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Socr. li. 2. ca. 8 Theo. li. 1 cap 11. Sozom. li. 1. c. 17. Nicep. li. 8. ca. 16. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe in the place befor: al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledged.</note> The lyke order was obſerued vnder that greate Emperoure Conſtantine, who withoute any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynte dydde permyt to the Eccleſiaſticall perſones free iudgemente in matters of faithe, and would neuer iudge of priuate complayntes made of any Byſhoppes in the councell of Nice. It is <hi>GOD</hi> (ſayth he) that hath conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted you prieſtes, that hathe geuen you power to iudge of vs, and not power to me to iudge of you. He is onely youre iudge, and you oughte not to bee iudged by men. Whyche holye opinion Valentinian the elder full welle did folowe, ſayeng: It becometh me not to iudge amonge the Byſhoppes, where any queſtion of the Faithe, or of Eccleſiaſticall ordre aryſeth: He ought not to iudge that doothe diffre in charge, but he whyche is of lyke voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is to ſaye, prieſtes oughte to iudge of preſtes. In the ſelfe ſame tyme, and to lyke effecte, Gregorye Nazianzene dydde preache before the Emperour Valens and tolde hym. The ordynaunce of <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> hathe made you ſubiecte vnto my power and to my iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: You are not he onely that ruleth, for we alſo rule in a greatter and more perfecte Empire, yf we dooe not ſubmytte the ſpirite to the fleſhe and heauenly thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to earthly. But geue me leaue moſte noble Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour more frankelye to vtter my mynde. I knowe that thou arte a ſheepe of my flocke, and in that thou dooeſt reigne and commaunde, thou haſte it by the benefyte and grace of <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> But wherevnto ſerueth this conference of kyngly or prieſtlye dignities, namely vnto vs, whyche neuer ne yet oure predeceſſoures haue at any tyme experimented of oure moſte Chriſtian kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges any vnſeemely enterpriſe, and that bee and doo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede in the ſtates of them, who neuer denyed the due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their kynges, no not once called the ſame in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.<note place="margin">The effect of his firſt propoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> Lette then (Sire) the firſte diſcourſe of this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bee to this ende principally that all menne maye bee wytneſſe in what reuerente ſort we humble oure ſelues. And howe muche wee woulde that bothe we and all they
<pb facs="tcp:25224:4"/>
that be vnder our charge, ſhould ſhewe their faithfull obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Let it be alſo a manifeſt declaration of the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that God hath left to vs in the guidyng of ſoules, in the doctrine of our faith, and that vnder your protection: to the ende that leauyng all other thynges aparte, I maye make you vnderſtande my charge, and by whom I am therevnto authoriſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SYRE,</hi> in this companie by your commaundement aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled we be a great numbre of Archbiſhops, &amp; Byſhops, vpon whom thimpoſition of handes haue ben layd by their Metropolitanes and other byſhops of the ſame prouince, and through the grace of Ieſus Chriſte, the holy ghoſt hath ben geuen, nominated by the kinges your predeceſſoures, who do ſuccede in the right of their people, they referryng themſelues to them, and into theyr handes: themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng diſcharged of all that is neceſſarie to their choiſe or ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: We be receyued vpon the view and conſent of our clergies and of our peoples that be vnder vs, after our inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution made by our holy fathers the Popes, and the holye ſee Apoſtolique, whom we acknowledge for our Superior, and all theſe ſignes and markes be accompanyed with one ſucceſſion from thapoſtles vnto vs very well continued. There be alſo a good numbre of prieſtes ſente by the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that bee abſent, and by the chapters and Clergie, and alſo Doctors of Parys (whom I name for honors ſake) and of other famous vniuerſities, and to theym all I am infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior in vnderſtandyng, knowledge, and eloquence, and yet neuertheleſſe by them all ordeyned to make you vnderſtand one thyng:<note place="margin">The vnity of the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lates and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>nce</note> wherin (thankes be vnto God) we be all of one harte &amp; one ſoule, &amp; of one fayth, vnder one God, &amp; vnder one head, our ſauior and redmer Ieſus Chriſt, vnder one onely Catholike churche his ſpouſe: hym we ſerue in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, vnto hym with one intention, mynde, and prayer, we bowe the knees of our heartes we worſhip and adore hym, and by hym we aſke the graces and gyftes of the holy ghoſt and haue no ſpotte of Idolatrie, howeſoeuer ſome men go about to lay vnto our chargs: Vnderſtande therfore Syre,
<pb facs="tcp:25224:4"/>
theffect of my meſſage.</p>
            <p>It is nowe eyght dayes paſſed that by your expreſſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce a certayne number of perſons were broughte into this place,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who of long tyme haue ſeperated themſelues from vs to our great ſorow and griefe, makyng a contrary profeſſion of faithe, and woulde not be obedient to our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and obſeruations, and yet in wordes ſhew themſelues as though they were deſyrous to lerne and to be inſtructed, reentryng into this their countrey, and into the houſe and company of their fathers, whom when they will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for fathers, they ſhall be receyued and embraced for children. Againſt theym we purpoſe not to obiecte any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche, but beare with their infirmitie: not reiecte theim, but call them agayne, not ſeparate them, but vnite theim, to thende that we maye all with one mouthe geue honor to God the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all charitie and ſpirite of mekeneſſe we anſwer, that we are verye glad of their profeſſion made of tharticles of the Crede, commune to all Chriſtian men, and doo deſire with all our hartes, that like as they dooe agree in woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, ſo alſo they woulde agreee with vs in ſence and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng, as it hath appeared vnto vs they haue not doone, by their definition of the catholike churche callyng the ſame to be the congregation of the choſen. After that they touched ſummarily diuers pointes cleane contrary to that whiche the Catholike church doth teache and beleue, and in ſo greate numbre, that beyng well compared vnto our profeſſion, wherof not to ſpeake without lawe, but to proue if accordyng to holy doctrine, euery poynte nedeth a whole day, and ſo the debatyng of this matter woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whole monethes.</p>
            <p>This hath ben the cauſe why at this tyme I haue charged my ſelfe of two pointes onely, whereof the principall is to ſeparate them, and to make them ſtrangers: thother is the only rule, wherby we may meaſure our controuerſies, and ſo come to agreement.</p>
            <p>This latter is of the Catholike churche, of the authoritie
<pb facs="tcp:25224:5"/>
of the Scripture, of the holy councelles, and interpretations of the fathers:<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3</note> whych point, I will firſte entreate of, and the other is of the veritie of the bodye and bloude of <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> in the holy ſacrament of the <hi>Euchariſtia.</hi> The one is the piller, the ſtrengthe the ſtaye and eſtabliſhmente of the truth: The other is the ſacrament of our vnitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge by hollye communion and participation of the bodye and bloud of our lord vnited and incorporated to our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, &amp; made all members of one body well compoſed and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing, wherof <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> is the head. It is ſix ſcore yeares and more before the counſell of Conſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which counſel there were ſome did affirm, that the chir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was of the choſen only, and that whoſoeuer was a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner coulde not be accompted of the church, and namely that a biſhop whom God had reproued, and ſo conſequently whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was a member of the diuell had no power ouer the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful: Ther folowed them other which, ſaide, that the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall churche was onely of ſuch as were predeſtinate.<note place="margin">Proffes that the Churche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in good and euil Mat. 3. Luc. 3. Mat. 22. Mat. 25. Ioan. 15. Eſai. 5 Math 2 Mat. 12 Luc. 2</note> Theſe errours and the renuers of them were in that councell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued and condempned as altogether wholy repugnaunt to the holy ſcriptures, wherin it is ſayd, that in the floure of our lord there ſhall alwayes be found chaffe with the corne, which ſhall continue to the ende, at what tyme the ſame ſhal be purged and clenſed by the fanne of <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> The flocke of our lord doth conteyne both ſheepe and goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; the ſame ſhall not be ſeperated vntill his return Al the world is bidden to the banket, but vpon the view which god ſhal make, he that is found euil apparailed, is driuen thens: Among the virgins were founde fiue fooles, againſt whom the gates were ſhutte. The vineyarde of our Lord hath not brought foorth good grapes, but alſo baſtarde grapes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was not only tilled by good huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d men, but alſo by euil whome god will deſtroy and let out his vineyard to others. And the kingdome of heauen which is the church,<note place="margin">Mat. 13.</note> is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to nettes: that gather fyſhe of all ſortes, whiche ſhall not be ſeperated or deuided vntill the nette be ful, that is to ſay, in the conſummacion and ende of the worlde, at what tyme
<pb facs="tcp:25224:5"/>
the angels ſhall ſeuer the euyll from among the iuſt.<note place="margin">2. tim. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And in this great houſe there be many veſſels, ſome appoynted to honor, and ſome to diſhonor. To be ſhorte among the xii. Apoſtles Iudas was reproued, and of hym it is writen in the actes, that the place of his apoſtleſhip ſhould be filled,<note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſal. 10<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; as the pſalme ſaithe, An other ſhoulde take his biſhoprike: And notwithſtandyng all theſe expreſſe teſtimonies of the ſcriptures contrary to this opinion ſundry inconueniences haue riſen, makyng this church to bee vnknowen and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſticall, wherby the ſtate therof ſhoulde be ſo vncertaine, that neither byſhops nor prieſtes ſhould be certayne, no aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured baptiſme, and all the adminiſtration of the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vncertaine. For Predeſtination or reprobation bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the higheſt ſecretes of God, the certaine knowledge wherof we can not attain. And notwithſtandyng this mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of good and badde together,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3 Ioh 14.16. Mat, 16. Mat <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Mat. 24 Marc 13 2 The 2 1 Tim 4 1 Tim. 3 2 Pet. 3. Epi 119. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>p 19. The fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and glorie of the chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Pro. 40. 2. Re. 22 Ephe. 6. Pſal. 119.</note> the churche ceaſeth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the ſayeng of S. Paul to be the piller and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the truthe, wherin ſhe is throughly inſtructed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt, and builded vpon that ſtone, againſt which hell gates ſhal neuer preuail: with whom <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> her true ſpouſe ſhall remaine to the worldes ende, although ſhe is aduertiſed by her lorde, and by the holye ſcriptures of the aſſaultes whiche ſhe ſhoulde ſuffer by meanes of falſe Chriſtes, falſe prophetes, falſe apoſtles, and of the abuſes, errours, and hereſies, which ſhould inuade her. Howbeit, as ſaint Auſtine anſwereth very wel to Ianuarius ſayeng, The Churche beyng ſett and placed among ſo muche chaffe and cockle ſuffereth many thynges, but thoſe thinges that be againſt the faithe or good life bee not by her in any wiſe allowed or made, wherin ſhe dothe neither howe her peace, nor yet diſſemble, vppon which ſence we acknowledge that ſhe can not go out of the waye, nor yet erre, eyther in the faithe, or in good lyfe, whiche we confeſſe and affirme as a thyng that no chriſtian man can denaie, and accurſed bee he that gothe about to obſcure her glorye and fame. The firſte place and chiefeſt authoritie belongeth to this ſhielde, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is the brandiſhyng ſword of all thoſe that put their truſt
<pb facs="tcp:25224:6"/>
in God. The true light which leadeth and geueth lyghte to our feete,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1</note> and is the lanterne of our waies and pathes: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to teache, to argue, to correcte, to inſtructe a man in iuſtice, that he may be perfect and redy to all the good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of God: and that it is the word of God which abideth, and ſhall abyde for euer,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 12 Pet. 10</note> whiche by the prophetes and apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hath been preached vnto vs. Moreouer, with this we acknowledge his ſpirite that geueth lyfe, and not the dead letter that kylleth.<note place="margin">21. Co 3</note> And to vſe ſaynt Hieromes owne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Lett vs not thynke (ſaith he) that the Goſpell is in the wordes of the Scripture, but in the ſence thereof. It is in the marowe, not in the barke or outwarde apparaunce of letters, in the roote of truth, not in the leaues of wordes. And this woorde of God we ſay, is of more antiquitie, and before the churche, as it appeareth in the creation of the worlde, and in the commandementes made to our fyrſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, howe be it the churche was long beefore any written woorde. For Moyſes was the fyrſt that dyd put the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God in writyng. And our ſauiour <hi>CHRIST,</hi> beyng a long ſpace in the worlde. And after his departure in long ſucceſſe of time his worde was taught and preached by the Apoſtles, after his aſcention, before they beganne to write, whyche gyueth vs to vnderſtande that the worde of God is as well to bee receyued and acknowledged of vs which is delyuered vs by the traditions of the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſoures vnwritten, as that whyche is lefte vnto vs in writyng.<note place="margin">8. The. 2</note> And we ought (ſaithe Saint Paule) to bold faſte the traditions whiche we haue been taughte eyther by woorde, or ſent by Epiſtle. In lyke ſorte as comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement to obeye and kepe theym is geuen in the Actes of Thapoſtles.<note place="margin">Act 15. 1. Cor. 11</note> And agaynſte ſuche holye traditions yf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny be founde contentious, lette it be ſayde vnto hym for a full aunſwere, we nor the Churche of God, haue no ſuche cuſtome, by aucthoritie whereof, wee knowe, what Scriptures bee Canonicall,<note place="margin">Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Lyrine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis.</note> and what bee Apocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall. The Cannon whereof, althoughe it bee perfecte and ſufficiente, yet oughte not the auctoritie of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng
<pb facs="tcp:25224:6"/>
of the Churche to bee coumpted ſuperfluous, for that the holye and ſacred Scripture, by reaſon of her hygheneſſe and maieſtie, is not all together receyued in one ſence and vnderſtandyng, by reaſon of the diuerſitie of opinyons in ſundrye ſortes of menne. Wherefore, it is very neceſſarye to addreſſe the ligne of thinterpretation of the Prophetes and Apoſtles, accordynge to the trewe rule and expoſition of the Catholike Churche,<note place="margin">quod v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bique</note> I ſpeake namelye of this churche Catholike, to the ende that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therynge the force and meanyng of the woorde, we maye holde that for Catholike and vniuerſall, whyche hath ben in all places where the Goſpelle hathe been preached,<note place="margin">quod ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per. quod ab omnibꝰ</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued, whiche alwaies and in all tymes, from the tyme of <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> vnto oure tyme of all menne hathe been approued and allowed: whiche ordre wee pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to followe and practiſe. In Vniuerſalitie if we dooe confeſſe that to bee the trewe faithe, whiche thole churche throughout the worlde dothe confeſſe. In Antiquitie (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng that whiche hath been ſayde and ſpoken in all tymes) yf we doo receiue none other ſence and interpretation, then that whiche oure honorable forefathers haue approued. In Conſente, whiche I ſpeake generally of that antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wherin we doo folowe the definitions and opinions of all the holy Martyrs, Byſhops and prieſts,<note place="margin">Aug ep. 118. cap. 1 ad Ianu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>arium. Act 15. Theffect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles. Mat. 18. chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logus ſer. 132. Nice. li. 15. ca. 19.</note> and all other our auncient maſters and inſtructours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THIS</hi> cauſeth me to ſpeake of the Councels, eſpecially of thoſe that be generall, the authoritie and vſage whereof hath alwais ben very holſome and profitable in the church. the ſame beyng inſtituted by God, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their auctoritie procedeth, &amp; firſt practiſed &amp; put in vſe by the apoſtles, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth in their actes: Al which being well conſidered what other thyng is it, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an aſſemble of all the paſtors &amp; doctors before diſperſed in the churche, and a congregation of them in one certaine place in the name of oure Lorde God? And if our Lorde haue aſſured and promiſed by his woorde one or two beyng gathered together in his name, to bee in the myddeſt of them: ſhoulde he refuſe to bee amonge ſuche then, as are farre better, and in more nombre laufully
<pb facs="tcp:25224:7"/>
aſſembled &amp; we ought truely then to crie oute with Dauid;<note place="margin">Pſal. 110</note> Great are the woorkes of our Lorde in the councell of the iuſte, and in their congregation. But it hath ben declared vnto vs, that not onely the prouinciall counſels haue bene corrected by the generall counſels, but alſo which is a more matter) that one generall counſel hath ben amended by an other.<note place="margin">De bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſm. 11 2. cap. 3.</note> We knowe this to be ſaint Auguſtins ſayeng, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we ſay is to be vnderſtand when there is queſtion of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes and of diſcipline, which do change accordyng to the tyme, and will be changed accordyng to the qualitie of the places, tymes, and perſons, as it is ſeene by experience, <hi>De ſanguine &amp; ſuffocato.</hi> But in tharticles of the faith and in thynges neceſſary to our ſaluation, the holy ghoſt is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector, in whom is no contradiction or contrarietie, and ſo we beleue it. That it is otherwyſe it ought to be proued or els no more ſpoken of. For if it were ſo, in vaine and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profite our ancient fathers haue had thervnto ſuche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and repoſed in them ſo great affiance in all the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries and calamities of the churche, and ſhould not therof haue founde by experience the ſucceſſe ſo happie. Of which good fathers that are gone before vs, behold what we ſaye, That euery of them was a man, &amp; ſo might erre. But that all in one ſelfe ſame article, or aſſemblie, in one ſelfe ſame do at diuers times diſperſed throughoute the churches haue erred,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Godlye counſell and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to knovv the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che.</p>
                  <p>Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Lyrine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</p>
               </note> we denie and mainteine it to bee impoſſible, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng the ſame vpon gods infallible promeſſe. Very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly therfore one among thoſe fathers for the concluſion of this purpoſe, dothe geue vs councell, and faith in this wiſe, What ſhall we doo (ſay the catholikes) if any parte of the churche doth ſeparate it ſelf from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall faith: preferre the body beyng yet holle before a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and ſicke membre. But if the ſore haue thupper hande and beginneth to attempt thinfection of the churche, then leane and cleane vnto the antiquitie, and returne to the mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers, whiche are the principall and firſt churches. Emong whom al the antiquitie hath had recourſe vnto the Romain churche, and hath alwaies accompted her to be the firſt and
<pb facs="tcp:25224:7"/>
principall among the Apoſtolicall churches, as Ireneus, Tertullian, and S. Auſten doo beare witneſſe, recountyng the biſhops vntill their tymes) who with all other auncient fathers haue alwais, acknowleged that churche as the chief See of all Chriſtendome, callynge the Biſhoppe thereof, <hi>Primae Sedis Epiſcopum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe if in this antiquitie there be founde any errour ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any author, or in any particular towne or prouince, then againſt ſuche ignorance and temeritie of a fewe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, lay the decrees of ancient and vniuerſall counſailes, and if in thoſe counſailes ye fynde nothyng, ſerche diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſentences of all the ancient fathers, approued by the churche writen to that purpoſe, and gather and collect them together from all tymes, and from all places, as thoughe they were all together preſent at a Councell: And that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che all they haue openly and at ſundrye tymes with greate continuance agreed, accorded, written and witneſſed with one conſent: Knowe ye that without any doubte ye oughte the ſame to beleue, and therevnto to ſubmitte and ſubiecte your ſelues. And aboue all thinges geue place (as they doo) to the expreſſe worde of God, and to the teſtimonie of the ſcripture. This is that we haue intreated concernynge the firſt point, This is the authoritie that we geue to the holye ſcriptures, to the determinations of the councells, &amp; to the writinges of the olde and ancient fathers: which order we purpoſe to obſerue, both for the confirmation of our flocks in the faithe, and alſo to brynge home agayne ſuche as are gone aſtraye, whiche can deuiſe none other waye to haue their doctrine and priuate interpretation to be credited and beleued, but to deſpiſe and condemn thautoritie of the hole, who reiectyng thantiquitie go about to bryng in eſtimation of their owne nouelties and deuiſes. A thyng truely where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Arrians were greatly troubled and dyd very well diſcloſe Neſtorius, Samoſatenus, and dyuers other,<note place="margin">Euſe. li. 7. ca. 30. Socrat. lib. 7. ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pit. 32.</note> and doubtleſſe ſhall reuele all ſuche as will diſcerne a ſtrawe in their neighbors eie, and can not ſee a blocke in their owne. Nowe I come to the laſt poynte of my oration, whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:25224:8"/>
it be laſt, yet in very dede the principalſt. We haue conceyued an extreme grefs and ſorowe, ſuche a one as can not be diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled, which is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt holy &amp; bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the <hi>Euchariſtie,</hi> which our lorde lefte vnto vs for a band of vnitie and of his peace: by a certaine curioſitie (I can not terme it more gently) of ſearchyng thynges aboue oure ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie,<note place="margin">Eccle 3.</note> which contrary to the counſell of the wiſe man, is made not onely an argumente of infinite controuerſie and altercatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo a right waie wholly to deſtroy the truth, or at the leſt to expel &amp; driue away the ſame. And in nothing els truly is the comon prouerbe (By to muche diſputyng &amp; debatyng the truthe is loſt) more ve<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied, than in this. For not onely the truthe dooth periſhe,<note place="margin">The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and bloud of Chriſt. 1. Cor. 10. Math 5. Ioan 6</note> but the fruite alſo which we ſhould therby receaue if we vſe it wel. which conſiſteth in foure poyntes. The firſte is the vnitie and reconciliation whiche we ought to haue and make one with an other. For it is written, that we beyng many in numbre are al but one body, which do participate of one breade and of one cuppe. And it is commanded, that when one dothe make his obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the altare, he ought firſt to reconcile hymſelfe to his brother. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is the vnitie with <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> Who ſayth, he that eateth my fleſhe, &amp; drinketh my bloode dwelleth in me,<note place="margin">1. Co. 10</note> and I in hym. The bread whiche we breake is it not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the body of Ieſus Chriſt, and the cup is it not the communion of his blood? The thirde fruite is the forgeueneſſe of ſinnes. For truly this blood is ſhed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſſion of ſinnes. The fowerth &amp; laſt is the attaynyng of lyfe euerlaſtyng. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth this bread (ſaith our lord) ſhall lyue euerlaſtyngly. All the contrary wherof cometh by this diſputation. Diuiſion among vs, ſeparation from god, priuation from the remiſſion of ſinnes, and from atteinyng of life euerlaſtyng. For out of the churche there is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and who ſo is putte oute of the Churche, he ought to bee vnto vs as a heathen or publican. And althoughe that in this poyncte there is but one onely and ſimple veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yet good God, howe many ſortes doo we ſee of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries? That woulde to God you woulde in deede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre them as you ſeeme by woorde in the .xxviii. article of
<pb facs="tcp:25224:8"/>
youre confeſſion prynted. Howe ofte doo they reproue one an others opinion, and yet howe ofte doo they change their owne? In ſuche ſorte, that in the expoſition of the wordes of our Lorde in his ſupper, they be ſo among theim ſelues deuided, that a manne way eaſily ſhewe you eighte opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at the leaſt, not onely diuers, but ſome of theim alſo cleane contrarye. Howe muche better were it to perſeuer in the opinion whiche the Catholike churche delyuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs frome the beginnyng, whych in few wordes is this.<note place="margin">The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment in the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning.</note> That the very and lyuinge bodye of oure Lorde <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> and his very blood is preſent in this holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and is there receyued. And theſe be thoſe reaſons beſides an infinite number of other, that kepeth within the vniuerſall churche in this ſimplicitie of confeſſion and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of faith, my reuerend brothers the archebiſhops and biſhops, and al other that befor the religion here aſſembled. Firſt and formoſte, the verye and expreſſe woordes of oure Lorde, This is my bodye, This is my bloode. Whiche wordes, yf they be not of ſo great force as they be in word and ſounde, why bee the ſelfe ſame woordes, and the lyke in all poynctes repeted by the three Euangeliſtes, and by thapoſtle Sainct Paule? Wherefore after the ſayenge of Saincte Mathewe, the fyrſte of the Euangeliſtes, Sainte Marke, Saint Luke, or ſaincte Paule doo not write after ſuche faſhion as oure ſacramentaries ſo longe tyme after would make expoſition, ſithens that it is not a thynge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the cuſtom of the ſaid Euangeliſts, that in a matter of farre leſſe importance, they themſelues ſometymes doo make expoſition, and ſometyme the writyng of the one is made playne by the other. As where the firſt and the thirde ſaythe, That it is a harde thynge, yea and impoſſible for a ryche man to entre into the kyngdome of heauen. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde (as it were) expoundyng the other, calleth hym the ryche man, which putteth his truſt in his rycheſſe. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther .iii. alſo doo ſaye, that that thyng which to men is im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſſible, is poſſible with God, The like alſo is to be ſene in other places ſufficientely, whyche for breuitie I do omyt.
<pb facs="tcp:25224:9"/>
So ſayth that holy martyr and philoſopher Iuſtin in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde apologie to the Emperor Antonine that the apoſtles haue taught vs in their writinges which bee called the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, that this holy meate which we calle <hi>Euchariſtia,</hi> is the fleſh, the body &amp; blood of our ſauior <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> But in this point there is muche more: And becauſe that in theſe fewe wordes <hi>(Hoc eſt corpus meam)</hi> ſpoken by ſaint Mathew and ſaint Marke there ſhould remaine no doubte, Saint Luke hath expreſſed the ſame by woordes,<note place="margin">The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geliſtes,</note> makynge therof no maner of doubt or ambiguitie. This is my body (ſaith he) which is deliuered for you, as though he wold ſay, not a myſticall bodye, as the churche is called by S. Paule, but the body of the fleſhe of Ieſus Chriſt certainly true and conceiued by the workyng of the holy ghoſte, of the pureſt blood of the moſt bleſſed and perpetual virgin Mary. This body of fleſhe I ſay, wherwith (the day after he ſpake theſe wordes in his ſupper) he dyd reconcile vs by his deathe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God his father. And here we muſt note that in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des there be foure things,<note place="margin">Fovver thynges to be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Pſal. 18</note> An hiſtorie written, plain, true, &amp; without doubt, a moſt clere &amp; euident co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Lorde, doth lighten and illuminate our eies. A Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of the teſtator, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ſtrength &amp; force. Which ought not to be ſo obſcure as to cauſe the heires to bee in controuerſie &amp; ſute about his will made ſo plaine and manifeſt by the wordes of the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> whereby we bee heires of God, and the coheires of <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> It is alſo a ſacrament, whiche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and exhibiteth that which it doothe figurate. Whiche foure thinges ought not to bee vnderſtanded allegorically, or ſpoken by parable, but the ſence thereof to be kept, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we obſerue, For nothyng can bee ſpoken more plaine. And yet notwithſtandynge ye wyll not acknowledge this ſence, who ſhalbe iudge of this controuerſie or rather who herein ſhold be more indifferent and iuſt, then our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune mother? The Church I ſay which went before vs, and hath regenerated vs all in Ieſus Chriſt. And this is the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall conſent of our old and holy fathers, beyng either aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled
<pb facs="tcp:25224:9"/>
in general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, or els write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by them whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were diſperſed throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches, &amp; in all tymes. And firſte touching the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, foraſmuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt .iiii.<note place="margin">Generall councels approue the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtes holy in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</note> general Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels be by ye aproued &amp; acknowleged. This ſame faith wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of we haue made profeſſion here before is writen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acts of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of Nice, which was the firſt, and in the councel of Epheſus which was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third. In al other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels which haue bene ſythens that tyme celebrated, there canne nothing bee found to the contrarie, albeit that alwaies euen before thoſe iiii. great councelles this doctrine hath ben thus preached &amp; ſo of all men written. And the churche of god during ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blous tymes wanted not falſe biſhops, falſe miniſters, and falſe chriſtians, louers of diſſentions and diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, who kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wing all kinde of Idolatrye had no more power to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble their faith herein then theſe holy biſhops to abide &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſame. And thus much touchyng Councelles.</p>
            <p>But which way ſhal I begin to enter in the teſtimonies of our fathers? ſhal I begyn fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this yere vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtels time, folowing the order and ſucceſſion of our biſhops and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the churches, wherein God hath bene called vppon? Shall I ſpeake of this laſte fiue hundred yeares, or of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fiue hundred yeres to a thouſand? Which no doubte be great in number, &amp; ſufficient to preſcribe againſt an Innoua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour. But you deſire an other thing. Let vs ſpeake then if ye wil ſtand thervnto, of the firſt fiue hundred yeres, which im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mediatly folowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doth of our Lord <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> Lette vs all make I ſaye of that moſt pure and holly tyme a councell, where the writinges of al our biſhops doctors and paſtours of all the churches (whether they were in Aſia, in Europa or Africa) be pervſed &amp; ſene, let vs folow the plurali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of voices of al their opinions, not onely in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy which we haue in this holy ſacrament, but in al other, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in oure payne and trauayle ſhall not bee greate,<note place="margin">Doctors and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of ſundry ages</note> becauſe we ſhall fynde theym all to agree. In the firſte hundred yeares let vs appeale and calle for the apoſtelles and their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, as S. Clement, ſ. Ignatius, and ſ. Denis. In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond hundred, Alexander the firſte, Iuſtine, Ireneus, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,
<pb facs="tcp:25224:10"/>
Origene, and Cyprian. In the thirde hundred yea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Arnobius, Lactantius, Euſebius, Athanaſius, ſainct Hyllarie, Emiſſene, Iſichius, Nazianzene, S. Ambroſe, S. Hierom, S. Auguſtin, &amp; S. Iohn Chryſoſtom. In the fourth hundreth, Leo the great, Proſper, Theodorite, and Cyrill. And in the .v. hundred let vs come to S. Gregorie: &amp; further more if ye will, let vs call Damaſcene, and long after hym S. Bernard. Theſe ſhalbe the iudges of our controuerſies, which be not to be ſuſpected: and of thoſe which be moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and ancient, ye ſhal haue a brefe repetitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or recital, to thintent ye may acknowledge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune &amp; vniuerſal agreement of the holie Fathers, there is no place or occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lefte vnto vs herein,<note place="margin">Hilla. li. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate.</note> to doubte of the veritie of this body &amp; blood. For by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of our lord, &amp; by our faith, It is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fleſh &amp; verily blood, which beyng receiued (<hi>Accepta ait &amp; hauſta,</hi> doo ſo worke and make, that we be in hym, and he in vs. Is not this tho truthe? But this can not be true to them (which wholly deny Ieſus Chriſt to be very God) and to be the ſame which hath alwaies been in the churche of God ſo generally in all mens mouthes, that amonge the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune faith, the veritie of the body and blood of <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> was not had in ſilence, no not by the mouthes of infantes,<note place="margin">Leo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 13</note> vnto whom, as to all other (for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhold not beleue it, &amp; much leſſe vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) it was and is daiely ſaied, and ſhall be vttered by the moſte graue authoritie of the Churche, that the ſame which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the fruites of the earth, and in the celebration of this ſacrament, placed vpon thaltare, receiued after the cuſtome of religion, conſecrated by myſticall praier, offred, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and after the celebration finiſhed, as it appertayneth, receiued to ſpirituall ſaluation, vſed or conſumed in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the paſſion, is the body and bloode of Ieſus Chriſt? whiche we perfectely beleue, hath appeared in the kynde of humaine fleſhe, and that this likour or drinke did runne downe and diſtill from the ſide of him that was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon the croſſe.<note place="margin">Augu. li. 3. de trini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te 4. &amp;. 10</note> Theſe good Fathers (I ſay) did teache their Auditorie to doubte nothyng at all before they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:25224:10"/>
communicate at this holie table of the veritie of the body and blood of <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 19 Leo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. 6. de Ieiu. 7. menſ. Chryſ. hom. 7. operis impfect 1. Cor. 1. Iſychius Leui. 22</note> For that is by the mouthe receyued, whyche by the harte is beleued. And in vaine they anſwer <hi>Amen,</hi> which diſputeth againſt that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they receaue. They made no difficultie to ſaie, that by the hande of the prieſt there is geuen and receaued, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which is ſeen, and ſanctified by him that gaue it: but alſo that whiche there is vnderſtanded, is that ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whiche ſanctifieth the receauour, euen the bodye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt of our Lorde, whiche as Sainct Paule writeth, was made a ſanctification for vs by the Father. Contrary wiſe doo they affirme, that he which ignorantly or through ignorance receaueth this holy miſterie there, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng he knoweth not the vertue thereof, yet the ſame is the true bodye and bloode of our Lorde <hi>IESVS CHRIST.</hi> In this wiſe &amp; thus plainly did the holy doctors both Greke and Latine ſpeake touching this matter now long ſithens. Whoſe words, ſpecially of ſom of them, we haue repeted ſo faithfully as we coulde. So plainly (I ſay) haue our ancient fathers writen, that one of them beyng the firſt,<note place="margin">Bere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Gu. Maling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berien. lib. 3 de geſtis Anglo.</note> which long time after the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did otherwiſe teach (that is to ſay) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, was none otherwiſe in this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but as a token or ſigne. And after he had therof wel aduiſed himſelfe, diſputed, &amp; reaſoned, did not only in his lyfe time, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge his opinion, but alſo at the point of deth, which is the time to confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth, or neuer, in his laſt words affirmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; ſtedfaſtly ſpake as foloweth. Truly we beleue theſe miſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries after the benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or eccleſiaſtical co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very body &amp; blood of our ſauior, being induced and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, by thauctoritie of thancient churche. We tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleue &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe acording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, by thunſpeakable operation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of god &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of his holy ſpirite, is in theſe holy miſteries preſent, geuen, &amp; recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, we paſſe ouer to ſpeake of the greatnes therof.<note place="margin">Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> i. 8<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Mat.</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhold ſeme to make our lord to be here outwardly vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, ſenſible, or perceptible. Nothing ſaieth a holy father, is here geuen vnto vs ſenſible: but vnder viſible ſygnes,
<pb facs="tcp:25224:11"/>
inuiſible thinges are there deliuered vnto vs.<note place="margin">Ho. 60 ad popu antioch</note> We abſteine alſo from ſuch maner of ſpeache, whereby contrary wiſe we might here ſeme onely to repreſent oure ſaid ſauiour, being abſent as in a tragedy or comedy. Truely the maner and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion wherby he doth here preſent him ſelfe to vs, wherby he geueth himſelf,<note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of Chriſthi being in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. Iohn. 1. Cy. li. 4. in l 3. ca 1, 14. Cy. Lu. 22 cita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te Tho. 3 parte que. 25 articu. 1. Ioan. 6</note> where by he is receiued and participated, is ſecret, not humaine or natural, and yet not therfore the leſſe true. We comprehend it not by ſence, reaſon or nature, but by faith. By which as the holy counſel of Nice the firſt of the foure chiefeſt dooth teache vs not to baſely reſpectinge the viſible elementes, but lifting vppe the ſpirit, we conſider by faith the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be of god to be there ſet in this holy table, taking away the ſinne of the world: and truly we there receaue his precious body and bloud. Better it is to follow the councell of the auncientes firmely to beleue the wordes of oure lorde god leauing vnto god of this his worke the meane, the way and knowledge: then in ſo highe a matter to thinke or vtter this Iewiſh word <hi>Quamodo,</hi> a worde (I ſaye) of increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; perdition to the Iewes, &amp; ſuch as follow them. Beleue ſaith the holy fathers vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe words ſo often repeted, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> Make no doubte thereat, whether they bee true, but receaue by faith the ſaying of our ſauiour. For ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he is the truth,<note place="margin">Bernat ſer. 2 de caena.</note> he cannot lye. Greate meruelies (my brethern) and thinges to be wondered at, are ſaide of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, faith is there neceſſary, Reaſon ſuperfluous, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge doth builde her foundation vpon reaſon, but faith vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon autority. Let faith therfore beleue, and ſerche not thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng. Theſe things (my brethern) do require neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily faith, and doth not admit reaſon. They require a ſimple beleuer, and reproue a curious queſtioner. We muſte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beleue ſimply that whiche cannot profitably be ſerched out. It is nto I ſure (I ſay) thus humbly to think and ſpeake. But ſeynge there be ſome that ſo highly do thinke, and more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behaueth as we ſuppoſe, queſtioning ſo much, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vs ſo neere of the manner of his preſence, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented freely to folowe their deſires, ſithens ſo muche a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt our myndes they thus force vs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25224:11"/>They cannot diſſemble but they &amp; theirs be greuouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with this worde <hi>Corporaliter,</hi> in this matter. But I take them to be men to muche exerciſed in the auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whereby they can excuſe theim ſelues, but that they haue founde that woorde expreſſed in their writynges.<note place="margin">Cy. lib. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. cap 13 in Ioan. H<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 8. de Trinita de Chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſtome <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hom. 15 in Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. 83. Hom. in Math. 60. ho. ad popu antioch</note> For the ſame and ſuche like be eft ſoones amonges them founde and repeted. Wherfore better it is with modeſtie to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete them, then to take them in ſo euyll parte. The fathers therfore both Grekes and Latins do denie, that the chriſten men haue vnitie of beyng or coniunction, onely by lyuely faithe and pure charitie, or, that (which is to one effecte) we be onely by faithe, hope, and loue, by religion, obedience and will, ſpiritually ioyned and vnited to him. But they with a more efficacie doo proteſt, that by the ſpeciall vertue and effect of this ſacrament duely and woorthily receiued, Ieſus Chriſt dothe really and in dede communicate himſelf to vs by true receiuyng and participation of the nature and ſubſtance of his body and bloode, and that verily he is, and dwelleth in vs: as we haue already ſayd, that theſe thynges taken and perceiued, maketh that we bee in Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> in vs, accordyng as he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioan. 6<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> he that eateth my fleſhe, dwelleth in me, and I in hym. For the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expoſition (and the ſame alſo to recommend vnto vs) of the ſaid dwellyng vnitie and coniunccion of hym with vs, and of vs with hym, they dyd not abhorre theſe aduerbes, <hi>Subſtantialiter, naturaliter, corporaliter,</hi> eſpecially S. Hilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vſeth to this purpoſe this worde <hi>carnaliter,</hi> that is to ſay, accordyng to the veritie of the ſubſtance and nature of the fleſhe of the bodie and blood of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: In ſuche ſort, that in no other place ſomuch or more then here, hath place, and is true and accompliſhed that whiche ſaincte Paule ſaithe. <hi>Quod ſumus Chriſti comparticipes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. 3 5<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cy. Hic <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. antioch.</note> 
               <hi>corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler (addo, (vt ita loquar) conſanguine<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) quia membra ſumus corporis eius, de carne eius, de oſsibus eius,</hi> That we bee of the ſelfe ſame fleſhe and bloode with hym, membres of his body, of his fleſhe, and of his bones. And we vſyng ſometi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes after, and with them theſe termes, we meane not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:25224:12"/>
or ſaye, that the maner of this ſo familiar and inwarde dwelling, vnitie and coniunction of oure ſauiour wyth vs, and of vs with him, ſhoulde bee therby naturall, ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, corporall, or carnall: but cleane contrarye we confeſſe it to be, &amp; more if it may be ſpoken then ſupernaturall, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, ſpiritual, inuiſible, vnſpeakeable, ſpeciall, &amp; proper to this Sacrament: not withſtanding true, &amp; not only figura<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiue, or ſignificatiue. And as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence, as little or rather leſſe we ſay it to be locall, circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcriptiue, diffinitiue, and ſubiectiue, or of any other phyſique, or naturall maner. To be ſhort in this matter we receaue no maner of <hi>Eſſe in,</hi> whiche Ariſtotle or anye other philoſopher hath. For as we haue already ſayde, we doo not comprehende it by ſence or vnderſtanding, by reaſon or nature, that this true precious bodye, and glorious bloud is here preſent, or exhibited vnto vs: but by the onely faythe grounded vpon the aucthority of the worde of God, which faith beyng ſo, is as Saint Paule ſayth it,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11</note> of thynges inuiſible, and not apparent, we beleue alſo that oure ſauiour geueth vs here his diuinitie, his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie, wyth all his goddes, treſoures, graces, and meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, inuiſibly, or by an inuiſible manner, true notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as we haue always ſayde: beyng aſſured, that euen as if we beleued it not, we ſhall neuer vnderſtande it, as the prophete doth threaten: ſo alſo if we humblye doo beeleue, we ſhall vnderſtand it,<note place="margin">Eſa. 7. Pſal. 83.</note> and ſee it aboue, when we ſhall ſee the God of Goddes (as Dauid ſayeth) in Syon. Which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge contrarye to iudgement, and ſpeculation of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng, and contrarye to the capacitye of mannes witte, and inward ſpirite, we muſt alwayes oppoſe and ſet the forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of theſe worees. <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> which ſhalbe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and lightnyng to all conſciences, in leauyng the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as the fathers doth teache vs, preachynge theſe wordes, Let vs beleue in our lord, &amp; obey him in al, &amp; through al. Let vs not ſpeake againſt him,<note place="margin">Chr. ho 60 ad po. 83 in Math.</note> although that which he ſhall ſay vnto vs, ſhal ſeme very abſurd, not agreable, &amp; cleanco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our ſences &amp; vnderſtandings. That his worde ſurmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth al thing, &amp; is to vs (as in dede it is) more worthy then al other things. Which thing is mete for vs to do in al things
<pb facs="tcp:25224:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but ſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy miſteries. Let vs not regard ſo much the things only which we ſee, but let vs kepe oure ſelues to his wordes. For his word is infallible, and cannot be falſe, or deceauable: Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywiſe the ſence is eaſy to be begiled, and oftentimes is deceaued. Seyng then he hath ſaid, This is my bodye, lette vs not doubte, but beleue and obeye: and wyth the eyes of our vnderſtandyng, beholde him.<note place="margin">Ma. 18 28</note> The pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prietie (I ſay) of theſe words, and conſequently the preſence of hys body here, dothe agree with the other places of the ſcripture, which ſpeke of his preſence with vs, and repugne not with any article of our fayth, eſpecially wyth that arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Aſcention of our lorde aboue all the heauens, and of his ſetting at the right hande of God his father:<note place="margin">The arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the crede not repugna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Chr. ho. 2. ad po.</note> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which articles ye ar the firſt (to my knowledge) in the remembraunce of manne, that euer obiected them, or made them to be repugnant, againſt the preſence of oure ſauiour in his ſupper. The holy fathers wer not ſo ſubtil, craftie, or curious: but ſimply, and humbly preached, that the ſonne of god together had his fleſhe when he aſcended vp to heauen, and alſo lefte it vnto vs in theſe holy miſteries. To be here, to be there, <hi>Surſum helias, Deorſum helias,</hi> ſaith one of them &amp; much better then Helias, who being rauiſhed into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire, did leaue &amp; caſt his cloke to his diſciple. They praied thus in the celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Thou, which ſitteſt aboue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father, &amp; art here conuerſant inuiſibly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, vouche ſafe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy mighty ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">Notable places of tha old fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers to proue Chriſt to be in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and here alſo in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. 103. de ſacerdo</note> to geue vs thine immaculate body &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious bloud. O what a miracle is this (they cried) O y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great goodneſſe of God. He whiche on highe ſitteth with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the ſelfe ſame inſtant, is betwene our hands, be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelf to all, which wil receiue him, &amp; doth this in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſight of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any deceit) or illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſe not but ther ſhold be here a faut, if the things there repreſented, wer not alſo preſent. They ſaid, Our lord hath lifted vp into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine throne that, which he giueth vs to eat, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth to be our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet we ar here remaini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. this roial bodi in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ther is wortht of ſouerain honor, is ſet bifore vs in erth, &amp; ſhewed to vs to ſee, to touch, &amp; to rate.
<pb facs="tcp:25224:13"/>
They introduced,<note place="margin">Sermo debre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate vite. ho. 55. ad po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pu. 15. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. ad Ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moth.</note> 
               <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> ſpeakyng in thys wiſe of this holy table to them, which camthither to receue, Eate me, drinke me, I haue lefte the in heauen aboue, and here in earthe beneath: I am ioyned and vnited vnto thee: not ſimply, or in ſuche ſorte as I am receiued of the, but I am diſtributed vnto thee, eaten and drunke of thee, in ſuche ſorte, that there is ſo great an vnitie and coniunction made betwene vs, that beyng ſo vnited and ioined, we are not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated one from an other by any meane or diſtance, but as of two made one. In this wiſe they dyd comfort the chirch, wandring here in earth like a moſt amiable ſpouſe, ſayeng: Thou haſte here in earth thy huſbande in the Sacramente, whom thou ſhalte haue in heauen withoute couer or vaille, and yet here verily, but vnder cloke and vaille, but there manifeſt. They were bolde thus alſo to ſpeake to the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande.<note place="margin">Bernar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dus 2. ſermons de caeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domin.</note> How chanceth this ſwete Ieſus, that we little wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes craulyng on the earth, we I ſay, duſte and aſhes, haue thee before our handes and eyes, and in the meane whyle, thou art all wholly ſittyng at the right hande of the Father, who in one moment of an houre, from the eaſt to the weſte, from the north to the ſouthe art preſent, and aſſiſtant to all men, one in many, thy ſelfe in diuers places, whence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this?<note place="margin">Amb. 1 precari. ad miſſi</note> Truely not by our meanes or deſert, but of thy will and good pleaſure, and of thy goodneſſe. They prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the prieſt, before he ſhould celebrate, to adreſſe hymſelfe in this wiſe to our Lord, with what contricion of hart, abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dance of teares, reuerence, chaſtitie of harte, and puritie of ſpirite, ought we to celebrate this celeſtiall and diuine ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, wherin thy fleſhe is verily receiued, wherein thy blood is verily drunke, wherin the higheſt thynges are ioyned to the loweſt, &amp; the diuine thyngs to the humain? Truely they that teache &amp; preache thus, douteth not, but that the body of our Lord, ſo many hundreth yeres paſſed beyng receaued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in heauen, is there, and here alſo together to bee vnto vs in this ſacrament preſent, preſented, and exhibited. If thou require the maner (ſo often to repete it,<note place="margin">Da<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. li. 4. ca. 14.</note> and neuer to attaine the knowledge? how this is done: let it be ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:25224:13"/>
for the to vnderſtand that it is the worke of the holy ghoſt. And we knowe nothyng more, than that the worde of God is true, of great efficacie, and almightie, but the maner ther of is inſcrutable. They thought nothing leſſe than affirme, that the ſaid body of our Lord came downe from heauen, or dyd remoue or depart, or that it was drawen out, as one of them ſayde very welle, <hi>Non quod ipſum corpus aſſumptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex coelo deſcendat. &amp;c.</hi> With whome we agree, and mynde with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make him com down, to pluck him from his fathers righte hande, or to aſſent to all other ſuche vnfitte and vnſeemely termes. For contrarywiſe, more than euery day in this holy miſterie, we make profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the faith which we beleue of thoſe articles, ſingyng, <hi>Qui ſedes ad dextera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patris, miſerere nobis. Et, Surſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corda. Habemꝰ ad Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And yet not withſtanding, they lay to our charges ſuche, and ſo vnworthy abſurdities, as though in this Sacrament, <hi>Nos Chriſtum Dominum coelo vel di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueremus, vel eliceremus, vel etiam deſcendere faceremus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thom. 3. part. queſt. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> artic. 3. Epiſt. 25.</note> For euen oure ſchoole menne dooe teache the contrarie. With like true meaning our aduerſaries woulde make S. Auguſtine of their part, alleagyng hym <hi>Ad Dardanum,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they can not be ignorant if they reade the whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle (as I doubte not but they doo) that there is no menci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at all made in that place of this holye Sacrament. And foraſmuche as ſo often tymes this holie man,<note place="margin">Leuit. 13</note> hath in other places, bothe preached &amp; written, we ought to draw out his meanyng touchyng this point, rather from al his other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then out of this epiſtle: the meaning wherof, we haue preſently anſwered, not wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng other ſolucions in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Of like ſimplicitie and true dealing be our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries here preſent, that is to ſay, being farre from Almaigne, and as one would ſay, contrary to the lawe, ſlaunderynge the deaffe, doo impugne that, whiche we doe not defende, that is to ſay, the <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> whyche for that it is not receyued in our frenche churche, we will leaue it to the princis and preachers of the holye Empire, which be called Proteſtantes to mainteyne, who at the leaſt in this poynte
<pb facs="tcp:25224:14"/>
doo agree with vs againſt them whome Germany together with vs calleth Sacramentaries.<note place="margin">Pref. 4. centur. Magde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgen.</note> And thoſe Germains ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly folowing the moſt plain, moſt true, &amp; moſt mighty words of our ſauior, do at this day conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly hold and main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyn the preſence, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; blood of our Lorde <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> to be in this Sacrament.</p>
            <p>But nowe I come to that point which you haue both here and els where written of this Sacrament, ouer and beſides that whiche is conteined in the confeſſion preſented by you in the name of you all. If you doo not eſteme Ieſus Chriſt, to be in this worlde touchyng the fleſhe ſince his aſcention, more than he was before his incarnation: If you do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue no other body then viſible,<note place="margin">De con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecr. diſ 2. can. Nos au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hoc eſt. Gala. 3.</note> albeit S. Auſten whom you would to be of your ſyde, calleth it ſo often inuiſible if you thinke it not to be otherwiſe, although more effectual in the vſage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacramentes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the preaching of his word, or if you eſteme theym thynges alyke, to put on <hi>IESVS CHRIST</hi> in baptiſme, and to eate his bodye and drynke his bloode at his holy table: To be ſhorte, if you or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do ſo faſten and lodge Chriſte onely in heauen, that in no wiſe you wyll haue hym founde vppon earthe, and ſo no more. <hi>In caena, quam in ſcena, Imo quam in coeno.</hi> Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wordes be not requiſite to be tranſlated, for feare of ſuch as be weake. we contrarywiſe, beyng taughte that the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is celebrated here benethe in this world, and not aboue in heauen: and beyng not ſo quicke witted, ſubtill, or wiſe, that we can comprehend a thyng verily, and in ſubſtance ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent from the ſayd ſupper, to be not withſtandyng veryly, and ſubſtancially exhibited and receaued: and for a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to bee there, and not to bee there, for feare to diſpoyle and euacuate the holy ſignes of thynges onely figured and repreſented: and not preſented or to be preſented, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, abſent, and ſeuer theym, as farre as heauen is frome the earth. Whereunto we anſwere you with like wordes, That we be as farre of from your opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this caſe, as the higheſt parte of the heauens is from the loweſt parte of the earthe. Or lette them all ſee and iudge whiche meaſureth
<pb facs="tcp:25224:14"/>
the pointes of our religion as they ought to be meaſured by Theologie, and not by philoſophie: whether of vs dothe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute more to Ieſus Chriſt our lorde &amp; god, whether ye or any other among you whiche doo mainteine that there is a place ſo preſcript in heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whervnto he is aſcended, wherin onely he is according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; els where he cannot be: or we, who although we beleue him to be in heauen, do not for all that ceaſſe to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is in all places where his holye myſteries are celebrated: and not otherwiſe, making no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inquirie of the maner, than as his omnipotent worde dothe teache. Graunt moſt puiſſant &amp; mightie god,<note place="margin">Auguſt. in pſalm. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in. de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſec di. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can. pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Ioan. 6.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as the firſt hereſie among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſciples of his ſonne our ſauior toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like occaſion of his worde, <hi>Durus eſt hic ſermo,</hi> which was ſo difficulte, that diuers of them murmuryng wente backe and folowed him no more, ſo alſo that this new and laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, This Sacramentarie warre (I ſay) which ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten dothe renew) take not away from vs thoccaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune accord &amp; conſent, of reducyng and appeaſing thinges to a better quietneſſe of our bodies &amp; ſoules, and to a more tranquillitie to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme, and aboue all things that it maye not trouble or let our reformation preſently in hand, which we haue begon in ſuch ſort, as it is moſt neceſſarie bothe for vs and our flockes. But principally that it will pleaſe hym to preſerue vs, that in theſe latter days and moſte perillous tymes that prediction doo not chaunce, whyche a manne of great name and eſtimation among our aduerſaries,<note place="margin">Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch. ad Oeco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lam. an. 1525.</note> diſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a companion of his in the beginnyng, to remoue from him this filthie tragedie, foretelling him, &amp; almoſte prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieng, that it threatned an horrible mutation, not onely to kyngdoms &amp; empires, but alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole church.<note place="margin">To Beza and his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantes</note> Me think I haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more troubleſom vnto you, by reſon of my lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wold haue ben: &amp; yet not ſo much perſuaded you, as I was deſirous to haue done, which if you wil w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie or reſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue, &amp; beleue no tyme of yeres paſſed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the death of our ſauior, &amp; from the primitiue church, vntil your owne ſeparation, we wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit you to your own choiſe. And if without cauſe for mainteining a quarel ſo iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:25224:15"/>
you haue vs in ſuch hatrede, and that ſo by open confeſſion, you will deuide your ſelues from vs, that we ſeme not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie in your ſighte to liue, or remaine with you, nor in the ſelfe ſame temples (I tremble at the ſpeakyng of it) to pray and make ſacrifice to God, and to adminiſter the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: yet at the leaſt refuſe not the Greke churche for iudge, in this controuerſie, if you ſo much abhorre the Latin, that is to ſay, the Romaine churche, takyng recourſe to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular churche, ſeyng the vniuerſall churche doothe myſlike you. What doo I ſpeake of the Greke church? Nay beleue the confeſſion of Auſbrough, and the churches that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſame, and you ſhal fynde your ſelues vanquiſhed of them all. But if you can not fynde place with them whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be deuided from vs: and that you agreyng with them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte in all other poyntes, and in this poynte of this moſte precious ſacrament you can not agree, what other hope of agreement with vs (but onely by wordes) can we conceue, whiche differ from you bothe in this, &amp; in many other poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes? And if you be ſo ſore addicted to your ſolitarie opinion, become in effecte ſolitarie: If you wille come no nerer to our faith, &amp; to our actions, get you alſo further of from vs, and trouble not the flockes wherof you haue no charge, nor yet any laufull adminiſtration. (For the ſame to vs apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth) according to the authoritie which we receaue from God. And geuyng leyſure to youre newe opinions to waxe old ſo long if God permitte it, as our doctrine &amp; traditions haue done: For we lay vnto you the preſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſens of the ſcripturs, with more reaſon than was done in Tertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians tyme, whiche ſhalbe a cauſe to reſtore peace to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubled conſciences, and to leaue your countrey in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe and reſte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To the kyng.</note>Wherein Sire, we all doo moſte humbly beſeche you in the name of God, by whom you are called to this eſtate, to holde your hande, and that it will pleaſe you to continue in this holy profeſſion of Faith, whiche we haue here preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared vnto you, accordyng to that whiche the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall churche hath ealwayes taughte, whiche is agreable to
<pb facs="tcp:25224:15"/>
the woorde &amp; ordinance of God. And in this ſo doyng, you ſhal reſuſcitate and in you plentuouſly reuiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graces whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che god hath placed in holy religion, not only in your gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, Quene Claude,<note place="margin">Quene Claude Quene Katha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine. Kynge Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the firſt. Kynge Henry the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde. Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ſecond.</note> and in youre mother Quene Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine our ſoueraigne lady, not onely I ſay) in that migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and wiſe kyng Francis the firſte your grandfather, in that good and ſo welbeloued Henrye your father, in that well condicioned kyng Francis your brother: but alſo in as many kynges, all your predeceſſors, and all our ſoueraigne lordes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that firſte kyng Clouis euen vnto you, of whom neuer was there one that ſtrayed from this holy Catholike faith, no not one euer founde to forſake the religion of his anceſters, and they all haue by ſucceſſion left and tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto you this name of moſte chriſtian kyng, and fyrſte ſonne of the churche. God almightie graunt, that your ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors maye receaue the ſame frome you in like integritie and perfection, and that our God vpon you our ſoueraigne lorde, nor vpon your ſubiectes, do exerciſe his mighty hand and the puniſhementes of his iuſte iudgementes. And you madam, ſeyng the whole realme hathe geuen vnto you all maner of adminiſtration and gouernement, during the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noritie of oure kyng and ſoueraigne LORDE, keepe vs well this iewell ſoo precious, and rendre hym agayne vnto vs, when he ſhall haue accompliſhed his full yeares, of the ſelfe ſame religion and fayth, wherin he is deliuered vnto you, and wherein hytherto you haue ſo carefullye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed hym. And herein you ſhall doo an acte ſo greate as that holy quene Clotide dyd, whiche is ſet before your eies to folowe, who by her holye inſtructions, was the meane and cauſe of bryngyng of Clowis her huſband to the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion. And you madame herein ſhall kepe the kyng your ſonne well inſtructed,<note place="margin">To the quenes mother</note> accordynge to the intente and will, of that good kyng Henry your huſbande. Wherfore madame, in the name of your ſaide beloued huſbande, we moſte humbly beſeche you, that lyke as we haue nothynge, that next after God more deere vnto your grace, than your commune, and euer pardurable and indiſſoluble loue, euen
<pb facs="tcp:25224:16"/>
ſo therfore aſwell in this poinct, as in all others, ye wyll fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe and execute his ſacred wille, and not to ſuffer his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to be condemned, nor yet the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of that migh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye kyng Frauncis your father in lawe which called you to the great and happy mariage of his ſon, to the intente their good expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in you, for the bringing vp of their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhould not be altogether fruſtrate and deceaued.<note place="margin">To the king of Nauar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and princes of the bloud.</note> We doubt not but in this doing you ſhall be well aſiſted by the king of Nauarre, &amp; by our lordes the princes of the bloud, who will not degenerat from their moſt chriſtian progenitours. The ſelf ſame counſail, wil thoſe noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue vnto you, which ar called to the honorable ſtate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel. The ſame alſo the Peres and officers of France, all which haue bene nouriſhed and aduanced by theſe good kinges, and therfore will call to remembraunce their will and pleaſure. And ye moſt noble and chriſtian aſſembly preſent, in this thing ſhal ſhew your ſelues not onely true chriſtians and faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes to god, but alſo moſt louing and harty ſubiectes to your king, wherby we al truſt by gods help that this whole realme ſhall bee ſounde in one vnitie. And to make an ende Sire we all with one heart, with one voice, and in the name of al the french church do vow vnto god, &amp; ſolemnly promiſe vnto your grace neuer to departe from this holy, true, and catholike doctrine. Which we will take payne to publiſh in our churches, and for the maintenaunce therof, we wil not ſpare to ſpende our hole bloud and liues, as in like manner we wil ſhew our ſelues alwais both redy and mindful tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching any affaires that ſhal concerne your maieſties ſeruice and the maintenance of your croune.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25224:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
